Let's get you set up!
In this module,
we'll go through how to install Rust using
rustup – a tool to manage
Rust versions.
We'll take a look at how to create new projects,
compile them,
and run them using Cargo – Rust's
package manager
and build tool.
We'll talk about where you can find documentation,
both online and off,
and we'll wrap up talking about the editor we're
using in this course – Visual Studio Code.
First things first:
the best way to install Rust is
with rustup.
rustup is a command-line tool to
manage the installation of Rust's versions
and optional components.
A new stable version of Rust comes out every
6 weeks,
and rustup makes it easy to stay up to date.
Visit rustup.rs,
which will give you a command to run that will
install rustup and the latest stable version
of Rust.
We'll show what this process looks like on Linux
and macOS first, then Windows.
On Linux and macOS, rustup.rs
shows a command for you to
copy and paste into your terminal
and run.
Feel free to first download the script
and inspect what it is going to do before
piping it to the shell to
run it, if you'd like.
On Windows, the process is a little bit
different. rustup.rs
will give you a link to download
rustup-init.exe.
Once you have that file, double-click
on it to run it, and follow the instructions.
At this point,
no matter what platform you're on,
you should have the latest stable version of Rust
installed by default for you by
rustup.
Open a terminal window.
Run rustc --version
and you should see a version number that looks similar
to what we have here.
Rust 1.24 is what we are using
in this course. You'll
likely get a newer version
and that's just fine.
The stability guarantees Rust makes
mean the code we write in this course
will compile and run successfully
with any Rust version
with a major version of 1
and a minor version of at least 24.
If any part of this installation hasn't worked
for you,
hop over to the Rust Beginner's chat on
the Mozilla IRC network.
We've provided a link to a web-based IRC
client that will take you right there.
The channel is full of folks eager to help people
new to Rust.
We highly recommend using rustup.
It's the smoothest way to install Rust.
However, if you don't want to use rustup,
there are other ways –
see the Rust website for more details.
Rust comes with a package manager
and build tool called Cargo.
Let's see what Cargo does for us.
First, check that Cargo is installed
by running cargo --version.
If you get a version number back, you're good.
The number won't match the rustc --version.
Cargo has its own version numbering scheme.
Next, go into whatever directory
you like to keep code in,
and run cargo new --bin
and pick a project name.
We've chosen the name myproject here.
This creates a new binary crate
that will produce an executable.
Binary crates are what we're going to be using
in most of the course.
The other choice is library crates
that are meant to be used from other projects.
You'd create a library crate by specifying
--lib
instead.
Cargo has created a directory
with the name that we specified.
So, change into that directory;
in here is a Cargo.toml file
and a source directory.
The Cargo.toml file contains some metadata
about our project.
Cargo fills this in
with information from your environment,
if it's available.
Feel free to fix any of this if it's incorrect.
Cargo.toml is also where we'd list
any dependencies
our project has. Right now, we don't
have any.
In the source directory,
Cargo has created a main.rs file
for us.
This file contains a main function that prints
"Hello, world!".
To have Cargo compile this code for us,
in the project directory, we can run
cargo build.
This has created some new files:
a Cargo.lock﻿, ﻿which we keep track
of the exact versions of dependencies that
were used, if we had any,
and a target directory.
In the targ﻿et directory is a debug
directory,
and in that directory is an executable
with the same name as your project.
Run that now and you should see it print
Hello, world!.
The executable is in a debug directory
because, by default, Cargo builds
with very few optimizations turned on,
which makes compiling not take very long
and produces builds
with debugging information in them.
If you plan on doing any analysis
of the runtime performance of your code,
make sure to build in release mode by
using cargo build --release
and use the executable that command creates
in the target/release directory.
When you're developing, it's common to
want to build and run the code often.
So, rather than running ﻿cargo build﻿
and then the executable,
there's a cargo run command you can use that
does both of those for you.
Throughout this course, whenever you want
a new project to experiment in,
follow the steps we just went through to get
a new starting project.
You'll probably have questions about Rust code
that these videos don't cover
at some point in this course.
When that happens,
try looking in the documentation.
There is online documentation at
doc.rust-lang.org
that includes API documentation,
error documentation,
and a number of free online books produced by
the project.
This information is also included
with every Rust installation,
and rustup makes it really easy to access.
In your terminal, run rustup doc
and that will open a browser window to the offline
documentation that's on your machine.
Finally, a word about the editor
we're using in this video series.
We're using the free, open source
Visual Studio Code IDE
with the Rust RLS extension.
The RLS is the Rust Language
Server – a backend that provides
information about Rust code to many
IDEs.
Visual Studio Code is the editor
that the RLS team has spent the most time
on so far.
In Visual Studio Code,
you'll get features like autocompletion
of methods available on a type
and immediate inline errors indicated
by red underlines
with the error messages available on hover.
Feel free to use whatever editor or IDE
you're comfortable with.
But if you're looking for an IDE, we
recommend giving Visual Studio Code
and the RLS extension a try.
You should be all set up now.
Let's write some Rust code, starting
with variables.