Welcome to Unit 2, Ownership and Borrowing.
In this unit, you'll learn about the concepts
of ownership and borrowing that you'll encounter
in most non-trivial Rust programs.
These ideas provide much of Rust's memory-
safety guarantees,
and understanding them will help you understand
many compiler errors you'll encounter.
A large amount of programming can be boiled down
to getting some data, doing something
with that data,
and returning some other data.
Consider a web browser:
it takes a URL that someone wants to visit,
it figures out where that URL is referencing,
and it fetches the HTML data that goes
with that URL
and displays it.
Every programming language provides a way
to manage this data, which includes
answering questions like: where
does this data get stored?
How do different parts of the program access
this data?
What happens to the data when the program
is done with it?
You can think of the different locations of data
management as your kitchen when you're cooking.
Working from the largest
and slowest to the smallest
and fastest,
we have the cloud,
or data available over a network.
This is effectively an infinite amount
of space,
but it's relatively slow to get data stored
there.
This is like the grocery store.
There's way more space there than in your kitchen,
but you have to plan
and travel to get ingredients from there.
Next, there's local disk space.
This is often in the hundreds of gigabytes
range these days.
It's not infinite,
but still a lot of room. Data
on disk is quicker to access than the
cloud, but it still takes some time.
Disk space is like your kitchen cabinets,
refrigerator,
and freezer.
You can store a decent amount of ingredients there,
but sometimes it takes time to find what you
need.
Next is RAM – your computer's working
memory.
This is frequently in the tens of gigabytes,
so it's smaller than disk space.
Accessing data in RAM is relatively fast.
When a program is running and actively
working on some data, that data is stored
in RAM.
This is like your kitchen counter, where you're actively
working on preparing food.
Managing this space is much more important.
You need a strategy for cleaning up as you go.
Otherwise, you'll run out of space and not be able
to do work as efficiently
or maybe not do any more work at all.
Rust deals with memory management using the
concepts of ownership
and borrowing.
And that's what we'll be covering in this unit.
In module 2, we'll define ownership
and explore the concept in the context
of the String type. We'll have an
exercise for you to try at the end of the module.
In module 3, we'll talk about possible
solutions to the exercise, problems
you might have run into,
and why solving this exercise is different
from other languages.
In module 4,
we'll get into borrowing. Borrowing
lets
other parts of the program access data without
transferring ownership. We'll show
solutions to the exercise that use
borrowing instead.
In module 5,
we'll generalize these ideas to data types
other than String. We'll talk about
slices of arrays
or vectors and borrowing of custom
types.
In module 6, we'll talk about the rules
around borrowing and mutability
that govern how to modify borrowed data
safely.
In module 7,
we'll demonstrate some code patterns that arise
due to how borrowing interacts
with the rest of our code.
And in module 8,
we'll explore how ownership actually applies
to more than just memory. This concept
helps manage resources like files
and sockets too.
By the end of this unit,
you'll feel comfortable
with the concepts of ownership
and borrowing
and be equipped to address common error messages
the borrow checker part of the compiler might
give you.
Now that we know what's being covered in this unit,
let's get started learning about ownership.