Let's get started! In the rest of this
module, we're going to cover what ownership means.
We'll talk about how Rust's system of ownership
differs from some other languages, such
as manual memory management in C
and garbage collection in Ruby.
Then, we'll get into some code
with the String data type. We'll show
how you can move ownership from one function
to another, and how you can clone data
to duplicate it
and, thus, have two separate owners.
We'll finish up by giving you an exercise
to try on your own before you watch the
next module, in which we'll discuss possible
solutions to the exercise.
So, what is ownership?
Ownership is Rust's strategy
for managing data in memory
and preventing common problems.
Every chunk of memory must have one variable
that is the memory's owner.
The owner is responsible for cleaning up,
or deallocating, that chunk of memory.
This cleanup happens automatically when
the owner variable goes out of scope.
The owner of data is also who is responsible
for deciding whether that data is mutable
or not.
Imagine a piece of data as a dish of
food that Jane owns.
She brings it to a party to share
with everyone. As the
owner of the dish, she is responsible for
cleaning up any leftovers
and taking the dish
with her when she leaves at the end of the evening.
One problem that ownership solves
is that leaving the dish around the host's house
would be rude
and mean that the host's house gets more
and more messy
the more parties they have. Eventually,
the house would run out of space to have
any parties in at all.
Cleaning up memory when you're done
with it is important so that your program
doesn't use up more of the system's
space than necessary.
Another problem ownership solves is that
the owner of the dish is responsible for
cleaning it up, not anyone else.
If the hosts decide to clean up the dish while people
at the party were still eating,
that would be rude.
You'd go to scoop another serving of the dish
and nothing would be there.
That's like one part of the program cleaning up memory
before another part is done using it.
Let's contrast this
with what other languages do.
We're going to look at C, which does manual memory
management, and Ruby, which has a garbage
collector.
In C, your code has to explicitly
perform both allocation
and deallocation.
When you want space to store some data,
you call malloc
and specify the amount of memory you want.
When you're done with that space, you call free
to return the memory to the operating system.
The advantage of this is that you have complete control
over when your program allocates memory
and how much it uses.
This control lets you write programs that run
quickly and take up the least amount of space.
However, having complete control is
also a disadvantage.
C, by itself, doesn't prevent you from
messing this up.
If one part of your program calls free
and another part tries to use that memory
again, that's called a "use after
free"
problem, and is like the host of the party cleaning
up a dish while people are still eating from it.
If you forget to call free once you're done with
the memory,
eventually you'll run out of space.
This is a memory leak,
and it's like bringing a dish over to someone's house
and never cleaning it up.
If two parts of your program try to clean up the
same data, that's known as a "double
free" problem and can cause memory
corruption.
This would be like the owner of a dish and the
host both trying to clean up the same
dish.
There are tools to help diagnose
and debug these memory problems,
but the C language doesn't help us out very
much.
These problems happen a lot and have caused
major security flaws and crashes
in lots of different kinds of software.
Just trying really hard to be careful
hasn't proven to be a very robust strategy
for software as a whole.
Ruby, on the other hand, takes care of
managing memory for you,
and has a component called the garbage collector
that runs alongside your program cleaning up
memory that you're done with.
The advantage of a garbage collector is that, while
you're writing code, you don't really have to think
about managing memory at all.
The garbage collector keeps track of which memory
is still in use,
and cleans up any data that your program is done with.
You also can't have
any of the problems we mentioned with C, because
Ruby is taking care of all that for you.
The downside of using a garbage collector
is that you lose control and performance.
When it runs, the garbage collector takes up
computing resources that your program
could be using. Your program will
also likely use more memory than
it strictly needs because the garbage collector
only cleans up memory when it's sure you're done
with it.
Rust is trying to get the best of both worlds
here. Ownership gives you control
over memory allocation
and the associated performance,
but by cleaning up data automatically
when the owner goes out of scope,
we can't mess up the memory access
and we won't be using memory longer
than we strictly need to.
Let's get concrete
with ownership by using strings.
A String is a type that has data
that needs to be cleaned up when it goes out of scope.
A String value tracks how much space
is allocated, how much of that space
is used,
and the UTF-8 data.
When the owner of the String value goes out
of scope, the UTF-8 data
needs to be cleaned up.
There are a bunch of ways to create a String.
One is by using String::from.
This code creates a new variable, named
a, and sets it to a new string
instance by allocating memory which
holds the text hello.
We can use the a variable, such
as by printing it out, until the closing
curly bracket of the main function.
At that point, a goes out
of scope and the data allocated for
the String gets cleaned up.
We can modify the String data by adding
more text to the String.
The variable needs to be made mutable,
and then we can call the push_str
method on a
and give it more text.
This will allocate more memory, if
necessary,
and when we go to use a, it will have
hello there! in it.
By default, with non-primitive types,
Rust moves ownership.
If we have the variable, s, holding a String, and
we create a new variable, ﻿t﻿, and
assign s to t,
this will move ownership of the String from
s to t.
Afterwards, the variable s is no
longer available to be used.
We've shown moving ownership in the context
of variables.
Now, let's bring functions into the mix
and see how moving also applies to
them.
Here's a function named say
that takes a string as a parameter
and prints it out.
This is different from the previous example,
where we did this in the main function.
When we call the say function
with a as the argument,
ownership is transferred from a
to s,
and the string data gets cleaned up at the
end of the say function.
We can verify this by trying to use
a again after calling
say in main.
Here, we try to print it out.
If we try to compile this code, we'll get
an error that we're not allowed to use a
because it's been moved into say.
We can also transfer ownership out of
a function by returning a value.
Here's a function that doesn't take any
parameters but returns ownership of a
string that contains the "heart eyes
cat" emoji.
Memory is allocated in the heart_eyes_cat
function, but it isn't cleaned up there.
Ownership of the memory is transferred to
a, and the memory is cleaned up
at the end of main when a goes
out of scope.
What if we wanted to keep ownership of some data,
but needed to also give ownership of
the data to another piece of code?
We can do that by cloning.
Cloning makes a deep copy of the allocated
memory.
Then there will be two copies of the data that
each have an owner,
and each owner is responsible for cleaning
up their data.
Cloning is one way to get around errors
having to do with moved values.
You may end up allocating more memory
than you strictly need to,
but you'll be allowed to do what you're trying to do.
As an example, when we wanted to use
a again, after transferring ownership
to the say function,
we can call clone on a
and transfer ownership of the clone
to the say function
instead.
This code compiles and runs. The cloned data gets
cleaned up at the end of say,
and the original data gets cleaned up
at the end of main.
It's time for you to get some experience
with Strings, ownership,
moving, and cloning
by trying this exercise.
Your task is to implement a function
that turns words into their plural versions
by adding an s to the end of the word.
In main,
you'll have a string like book,
and your goal is to get main to print
I have one book,
you have two books, by calling
your pluralize function.
Note that the String type has a method
called push_str that you might
find useful.
It's not the only way to complete this exercise,
though.
If you get compiler errors while working on
this, or if you get stuck, that's
great! In the next module,
we'll be going through some of the problems you might
run into while working on this exercise.
Now you've learned how Rust's ownership
differs from manual memory management
and garbage collection, as well as the basics
about String.
Apply what you've learned about moving
and cloning as you try the exercise
before the next module.