In this module,
we're going to go into detail about the slice data type. In unit 1, module 4, we briefly mentioned the slice
primitive data type.
Slices borrow data. So, now that you know about borrowing,
we can cover slices more thoroughly. In this module, we'll talk about what a slice is and how to create them.
We'll show why it's a good idea to use slices as parameter types in functions or methods.
And we'll discuss how we were able to borrow a String in the last module and pass that to a function with a string slice as a parameter type.
So, what is a slice?
A slice is a data type that always borrows data owned by some other data structure,
such as the String type that we covered in module 2.
A slice consists of a pointer and a length.
The pointer is a reference to the start of the data that the slice contains,
and the length is the number of elements after the start that the slice contains.
This slice contains the two ls from the hello string.
Now that we know how a slice is stored,
let's look at how to create a slice in code.
Even though a slice is stored as a pointer and a length, in code,
we create a slice using an ampersand,
the variable we're referencing, and square brackets containing a range.
In this case, the starting index is 2, and the ending index is
4.
If the slice you create starts at index 0,
the starting index is optional,
and you can just put two dots and the ending index.
If the slice you create goes all the way to the end of the data structure,
the ending index is optional.
To make a slice that borrows all of the data,
all you need inside the square brackets are two dots.
We can also create slices from arrays and vectors. Recall from unit 1, module
4, that arrays are fixed-length collections where all of the elements have the same type,
such as this array of f64 values.
We also mentioned in that module that vectors are similar to arrays but can grow or shrink in size,
such as this vector of i32 values that we can add an element onto. Creating a slice from an array or vector is similar to creating a slice from a string:
use an ampersand, then a range and square brackets.
Like plain references, the borrow checker ensures slices are always valid. At runtime,
Rust will panic and stop your program
if slice indices are out of bounds.
These protections prevent bugs.
Let's look an example of trying to use invalid indices.
In this program,
we have a vector containing three elements,
and we try to create a slice up to index 9.
Even though we, as humans, can see that index 9 is going to be out of bounds in this example,
Rust does not analyze the index with the slice when it compiles the code.
If we had used a value provided by the user of the program rather than hardcoding the index
as we have here,
Rust wouldn't even be able to do an analysis at compile time.
This code will compile without any errors.
Slice indices are not analyzed at compile time.
However,
when we run this program,
it panics with the error index 9 out of range for slice of length 3.
Because Rust can't prove the slice indices are valid at compile time,
it checks the slice indices at runtime and deliberately terminates the program
if they're invalid.
This prevents the use of invalid memory,
which would lead to seg faults or undefined behavior.
String slices have an additional protection.
The indices of the slice range must be at valid Unicode character boundaries.
In this code,
we have a string literal containing emoji,
each of which use multiple bytes.
We then attempt to create a slice from 0 to 1.
This code also compiles.
Character boundaries aren't checked at compile time
either.
When we run the program,
it panics with the error message
byte index 1 is not a char boundary. To ensure your program doesn't panic,
consider using methods on String, like chars or char_indices,
rather than slicing at arbitrary indices.
In general, it's better to use a slice or a string slice as parameters to functions or methods, rather than borrowing a Vec, array, or String. Let's look at why.
This function,
named only_reference_to_array,
has a parameter with the type of a reference to an array of three i32 values.
That's the only type that this function will accept.
This function,
named only_reference_to_vector,
also borrows its parameter.
But this function will only accept a reference to a vector containing some number of i32 values.
In contrast,
this function,
named reference_to_either_array_or_vector,
has a slice of i32 values as its parameter.
This function can be called with some number of i32 values borrowed from either an array or a vector.
It can even be called with a slice of a slice.
As you can see from this usage of each of the functions,
using a slice as a parameter gives callers more flexibility and means functions can be used in more contexts.
Similarly,
by specifying string slices as parameters rather than borrowing an ownedString,
functions can accept either borrowed strings or string literals.
String literals create string slices.
Their text appears in your compiled program,
which is also stored in memory, just like your data.
The string slice points to this literal text.
Finally,
you may have been wondering how we're able to call functions that take a string slice by passing an argument that is a reference to an owned String.
This is due to a combination of features Rust provides to make using slices more ergonomic.
We're going to discuss how this works at a high level.
First, the standard library includes the implementation of a trait called Deref on String,
such that Rust knows how to convert
a reference to a String into a string slice containing the whole String.
Next,
Rust has a feature called deref coercion.
This means that when you call a function or method,
the compiler will automatically dereference the arguments,
if need be,
to convert them to match the function parameter type.
This is why we were able to call the pluralize function in the last module,
even though it took a string slice as its parameter type,
and we had an argument of a reference to an owned String.
This works for arrays and vectors
too.
For example,
earlier
when we called the either_array_or_vector function,
we actually didn't need the square brackets and the range. A reference to the array or vector coerces to a slice of the whole array or vector.
See the Deref traits documentation ﻿for other implementations.
In this module,
you learned that a slice is a way to borrow a contiguous chunk of data owned elsewhere.
You know how to create a slice using an ampersand,
square brackets, and a range.
We demonstrated that using slices as parameters makes functions more flexible, and how the Deref trait and deref coercion combine to make slices ergonomic to use in common situations.
In the next module,
we'll talk about how borrowing interacts with mutability.