So far,
we've only talked about immutably borrowing
a value to read it.
It's also possible to mutably borrow a value in order to change it without taking ownership. In this module, we'll show you how to create and use a mutable reference.
We'll look at an example using a function,
and an example of a method where the first parameter is a mutable
reference to self.
In order to ensure memory-safety,
the compiler enforces some rules around
mutable references. We'll go over those.
Lastly,
we'll discuss an example of some code that doesn't compile because of the borrowing rules,
and talk about the bug the compiler prevents in that situation. Let's get started with how to create and use a mutable reference.
Recall from unit 1,
module 3,
that in order to make a variable mutable,
we use the mut keyword in a let statement.
Similarly,
to create a mutable reference,
we add mut after the ampersand.
Let's look at an example of a function that needs to use mutable references. In this example, we have defined a struct named Bucket that has a liters field to store how much liquid is in the bucket.
The #[derive(Debug)] annotation on the struct definition enables us to print out the values of a Bucket for inspection later.
We've also defined a function named pour that takes references to a source and target bucket, indicated with the ampersand.
The function also takes an amount to transfer from the source to the target.
The body of the function subtracts the amount from the source bucket's liters field and adds the amount to the target bucket's liters.
In the main function, we instantiate
two buckets and then pass references as arguments to the pour function, again, using the ampersand.
If we compile this,
we'll get errors that say we cannot assign to the liters field of immutable binding.
The compiler also suggests that we change from an immutable reference to a mutable one.
We replace the ampersands in the definition of pour with &amp;mut; the same replacement when we call pour; and make each of the buckets mutable, using the mut keyword.
When we run this code,
we can see that calling
the pour function has moved three liters from Bucket 1 to Bucket 2.
Another common way mutable references are used is as the first parameter of methods, as &amp;mut self,
so that these methods can modify the current instance.
We touched on this briefly in unit 1, module 9,
but here's another example.
We've defined a CarPool struct to model people sharing rides to work.
The struct holds a vector of strings,
representing the names of the passengers currently in the vehicle.
We've defined a method named pick_up on CarPool that takes a mutable reference to itself
so that this method can change the fields of the current CarPool
instance.
The method also takes the name of a passenger,
and the body pushes the name into the passengers
vector. In the main function, we've instantiated
a new mutable instance of a CarPool, named monday_car_pool,
that doesn't have any passengers.
Then, we've called the pick_up method to add passengers to the vehicle.
When we run this,
we can see that the CarPool accumulates
passengers
as we call the pick_up method.
Notice that because of the way methods work,
we don't have to create a mutable reference to monday_car_pool explicitly
with &amp;mut
when we call pick_up.
Rust creates the reference automatically for the self parameter,
and it knows to make it mutable as well.
This may make it hard to tell which methods mutate self,
but you can always find out by looking at the signature of the methods in the API documentation.
The compiler enforces some rules involving mutable references.
Let's explore those now.
The rules are that, when you have a reference,
you can either have any number of immutable references to a value or a single mutable reference to that value.
To understand why these rules are necessary,
imagine an art class where the students are painting a bowl of fruit set up in the middle of the room.
Any number of students can look at the bowl of fruit at the same time to work on their painting.
Because none of the students are changing the fruit setup,
they don't interfere with each other.
This is like having many immutable references to the same value.
If someone comes in in the middle of a class and rearranges the fruit,
none of the students would be able to finish their paintings because the scene they were referencing is now different.
This is what would happen if a mutable reference was allowed at the same time that there were immutable references,
which would cause bugs.
Changing the fruit's position should only happen before or after class, when there are no students.
Even
if there weren't any students trying to paint at the time,
if multiple people were changing the fruit setup at the same time,
they could also conflict with each other and cause problems.
This is why only one mutable reference is allowed at a time.
Let's look at some code that doesn't compile because of these rules,
to better understand the problems that Rust prevents.
Here, we have a vector named list that contains the values 1, 2, and 3.
We also have a for loop that iterates over the values in the list. For each value,
the body of the loop prints out the current item and then adds to the list the current item plus one.
If this code was allowed to compile and run, on the first iteration of the loop,
i would be 1. The code
would print out i is 1 and then would push 2 onto the list, making the list 1, 2, 3, 2.
Continuing to execute the code would make the vector grow continuously,
and we'd have an infinite loop. This is likely not what we intended to happen with this code,
but that's not even the real problem.
Let's look at the error message the compiler gives us when we try to compile
this code. It says, cannot borrow `list` as mutable because it is also borrowed
as immutable.
The immutable borrow of list occurs in the for loop,
and the mutable borrow of list occurs when we call list.push.
Another way
we could have figured out that the push method takes a mutable reference to its target
is by looking at its documentation.
The signature shows that this method takes a mutable reference to self.
The real problem has to do with the management of the memory backing the vector,
which looks something like this.
Here's the immutable borrow that the for loop takes and the mutable borrow that the push method takes. When you have a mutable borrow,
one of the aspects of the vector's data structure that could change is the pointer to the heap data.
If the vector has been filled to capacity,
and we call push to add a new value,
the implementation of push may need to allocate more memory, and change the pointer to point to the new storage location.
At this point,
the immutable reference that the for loop has to the vector now points to invalid memory.
This is memory unsafety that could cause seg faults,
but the Rust compiler prevents that. This particular bug is called iterator invalidation and is a problem in many languages,
but not in Rust.
We've now covered how borrowing and mutability interact.
We've shown how to use mutable references in functions and methods.
We've talked about the borrowing rules that say you can either have multiple immutable references or one mutable reference.
And we've looked at an iterator invalidation bug that Rust disallows by enforcing the borrowing rules. In the next module, we'll demonstrate some common code patterns that arise due to borrowing.