Welcome to module 2, An exploration of concrete lifetimes. In this module,
we're going to discuss what we mean when we talk about concrete lifetimes of values and references.
After we've defined concrete lifetime,
we're going to annotate the concrete lifetimes in code
examples for values and their references. We'll show what concrete lifetimes look like with all the code in one function
and when the code uses multiple functions.
Let's get started with the definition of concrete lifetimes for values.
First,
let's discuss what "lifetime" means in Rust,
which is slightly different than the general meaning of the word in English and the meaning in other programming languages.
In Rust, a value's lifetime is the time during which the value exists at a particular memory address.
You can think of the validity of a memory address as similar to the validity of a person's home address.
When you're born,
you live at a particular address.
At some point,
you might move to a different address.
If someone had your old address and tried to visit you,
you wouldn't be there.
Over your life, you will live in many houses and have many different addresses.
When you die,
you will also move out of your house and your address will cease to be valid one last time.
Correspondingly,
the concrete lifetime of a value in code starts when a value is created or moved into a particular location in memory, and ends when that value is moved out of or dropped from that location.
This maps directly to the concepts of ownership, moving, and dropping that we discussed in unit 2 in the Ownership module.
Now, let's talk about concrete lifetimes for references.
It turns out that references are values, so the definition of the start and end of a reference's
lifetime is the same as for values.
It lasts from when the reference is created or moved into its memory location and ends
when the reference is moved or dropped.
However,
there's an additional constraint for references.
A reference's lifetime must be contained within the lifetime of the value being referenced.
This constraint ensures every reference will always point to a valid value.
Let's take these definitions and show what they look like
in code,
starting with two examples where all the code is in one function. In the first example,
we'll show a straightforward reference to a vector. We create a vector of numbers and bind it to the variablelist.
We can use this vector by printing it out.
This value's lifetime, annotated in blue,
starts from the line where we create list until the closing curly brace of main,
where list goes out of scope and the value gets cleaned up.
Next,
let's create a reference, specifically,
a slice to the first two elements in the vector and bind it to the name first_two.
We can use that reference in various places after it's created.
The reference has its own lifetime,
but it's also tied to the lifetime of the value it references.
So we're going to annotate the lifetime of first_two as a blue dotted line.
This lifetime starts where first_two is created and continues until the end of the function,
where it gets cleaned up just before list is cleaned up.
The reference's lifetime is shorter than the lifetime of the value of first_two, so this example compiles and the reference is always valid.
The second example is a slight variation on the first example. This time, we'll create the reference within an inner scope.
The concrete lifetime of list is still from where list is created until the end of main.
The lifetime of the reference starts where we create
first_two.
But this time, the lifetime ends at the closing curly brace of the inner scope.
The reference's lifetime is still shorter than the lifetime of the value it refers to, so this
example is valid as well.
This example shows that a reference's lifetime might end well before the value's lifetime ends.
Next,
let's look at two more examples to see what lifetimes look like across function calls.
The third example is a variation on the second example.
We extract the inner scope into its own function called
print_first_two.
The lifetime of list is still the same.
Each of the two times we call the print_first_two function,
we pass it a reference to list,
so two references tied to the lifetime of list are created on these lines.
Each of these lifetimes are shorter than the lifetime of list,
so these references are valid.
Next,
we're going to annotate the lifetimes in the print_first_two function independently of where print_first_two
is called. The borrowed_list parameter's
lifetime starts at the beginning of the function and ends at the end of the function.
It's a reference tied to some value from where it's called,
so we're going to annotate it with an orange dotted line. We create the first_two slice from the parameterborrowed_list.
The lifetime of first_two is tied to the same value that the lifetime of borrowed_list is tied to, so we're also going to annotate it with an orange dotted line.
The lifetime of first_two starts when we create it and goes until it goes out of scope at the end of the function, just before borrowed_list does.
The difference between analyzing lifetimes when the code is all in one function and the code is in another function, is that when we write the function,
we don't necessarily know about everywhere it'll be called.
But when we do have main and compile it,
the borrow checker analyzes the concrete lifetimes at each call and connects them to the lifetimes in the function.
Because we're calling the print_first_two function with references to list,
we know the orange dotted lifetimes in the function are tied to the lifetime of list, so we're going to change them to blue dotted lines.
The third example was a function that didn't return anything.
The fourth example has a function that returns a reference.
The return_first_two function
takes a slice and returns a slice of the first two elements of the parameter.
In main,
we call return_first_two and store the result in the first_two variable,
then print it out.
The lifetime of list is still the same.
We create a reference to list and pass it to the return_first_two function,
so that's where our reference's lifetime starts – tied to the lifetime of list.
In the ﻿return_first_two ﻿
function, the borrowed_list parameter's
lifetime starts at the beginning of the function and ends at the end of the function,
annotated here with an orange dotted line because it's tied to some value outside of the function,
just like in example
number 3.
Then, we create and return the slice reference to the same value borrowed_list references.
This reference's lifetime is also annotated with an orange dotted line because it's tied to the same value borrowed_list
is.
This lifetime comes out of the function with the returned reference.
Going back to main, the return value of the return_first_two function is bound to the first_two variable. Because we passed a reference to list to the return_first_two function and the implementation of return_first_two returns
a reference tied to the same value as
its parameter, first_two is a reference that is tied to the lifetime of list.
Therefore,
we replace the orange dotted lines with blue dotted lines.
The lifetime of first_two is shorter than that of list,
so this code is valid.
In this module, we talked about how "lifetime" in Rust means the time a value is at a particular location in memory.
We discussed how references must have a lifetime contained by the lifetime of the value they point to.
And we looked at examples of concrete lifetimes of values and references in one function and across multiple functions where the references were valid.
In the next module, we'll show examples where references aren't valid, and we'll use the same visualizations to understand why the examples don't work.